[Music]
hello good evening good day to everybody
welcome to a new episode of the ask
abhijit show
i hope you're all doing very well and
let me see who all is there today with
us
i can see akanksha dungar singh johann
watsal abhinash avantika
h8x proful
avinash
gk blue bird asmanor
harbinger varun sharma
watsal avantika bibek
and lots of other people good evening
good day to all of you i hope you're
doing well
and before we begin please let me know
if there is any issue with the image
quality we had a couple of live streams
in which the image wasn't very good so
that was
unfortunate i hope that doesn't happen
again
so if there is any problem please let me
know i will keep an eye on the
on the chat messages
so just let me know if the image is fine
or if there is any problem with the
image
all right
so i think there are no issues that's
what people are saying no problem thank
you so much thank you so much great
so with that let's get into the
questions i have taken a bunch of
questions and let's see how many i can
answer today
question one is from yuraj singh a 5 000
year old jewellery factory has been
found in rakhigarhi what's my reaction
to this my reaction is yay great
fantastic
we found a jewelry factory the thing is
this rakari is the most likely the
largest known
uh saraswati sindhu civilization ira
site archaeological site that we know of
and i think we have excavated or
explored only like two or three percent
of it
so
the majority of this site is still
underground and we still don't know much
about it so as we explore and excavate
this site further we will find
uh more such
interesting artifacts emerging from it
so we discovered a jewelry factory there
are so many other sites there are
thousands of unexplored
unexcavated archaeological sites along
in this entire region so as we explore
and excavate more of them we'll find
lots of other interesting things
jewelry factories and uh i don't know we
will be able to uncover the lifestyle of
our ancestors what sort of live lives
did they live and so on right now we
know very little about them so this
jewelry factory they have found they
found i think gold ornaments and the
entire
tools for making these uh
various ornaments and things that's what
i heard i haven't read the news in
detail but it's not surprising and i'm
very happy to see this
so i hope the
excavation the archaeological work goes
on it carries on and we we explore many
more sites apart from vacagari
so it needs to go on and it's a very
good and welcome development
summer says
why did india ban wheat exports is it
because of the heat wave or the cyclones
that we've witnessed before
about a week ago the government said we
were ready to feed the world so what's
happening is it a loss for us g7
countries have started to criticize us
for banning the wheat exports
why do they have a problem on about this
when they should understand that india
has to take care of its own people first
okay let's first go into why this was
done
so uh
it has nothing to do with cyclones as
far as i understand the heat wave yes
there's been there's been a heat wave in
recent days and weeks in northern india
and in other parts of india as well so
that has affected the the wheat crops
and uh so that's one factor the larger
factor
is that uh
the past two two and a half years ever
since 2020 we went through this terrible
unfortunate pandemic
in which the entire country was under
lockdown for a long period of time for
on various occasions
and because of that the government of
india was forced to dip into its
food grains reserves
and i think it dispersed free
food grains including wheat to about 800
million people because people were
jobless people were not working anymore
and that's how the nation was able to
tide over this this terrible crisis
so the food grain reserves have gone
down
and because of this
situation in ukraine
ukraine is one of the major wheat
exporters in the world now the ukrainian
wheat exports are not happening because
of the war which which is going on there
the ports are blockaded and so on
and therefore uh wheat prices and other
food grain prices are rising inflation
is rising worldwide india is also
dealing with somewhat increasing
inflation
and if we keep on exporting our food
grains
then the prices will go will rise even
further i think the prices have risen to
record levels when it comes to uh
when it comes to wheat so to
prevent this from happening the
government of india has temporarily this
is a temporary van this is this is a
temporary ban they have we have
temporarily uh banned the export of
wheat so this is not a complete blanket
ban
uh wheat exports will be still allowed
on a case-by-case basis there will be
some nations that have desperate
shortages of wheat and all that so in
case there are situations like that in
certain places then we will allow
exports of wheat on a humanitarian basis
to such countries but there is a crisis
situation so that is something we're
going to do but we are not going to
allow the unabated
uh full-scale export of wheat i think
india is india is i think the second
largest
producer of wheat in the world and the
sixth or seventh largest exporter of
wheat
so right now india has to look out for
its own people first india has to ensure
that the inflation doesn't rise too much
india is to ensure that the wheat prices
and food grain prices don't rise too
high because that's going to
impose lots of hardships
on on people on on the population of
india we don't want that to happen so
temporarily we have banned the export of
wheat eventually in the future when
things are better as judged by the
government of india we may allow
the export of wheat to resume right now
it is going to be allowed on a
case-by-case basis only when in place in
cases where certain countries have a
genuine
crisis
kind of situation
so that is the reason why india has
temporarily banned the wheat exports now
you are right
uh several g7 countries uh are
criticizing india for banning wheat
exports india has a responsibility to
the g7 or whatever
india owes nobody anything
india has a responsibility to its own
citizens
india's india's interest comes first the
national interest comes comes first as
it has always been across the world
when the
corona virus crisis was going on the
americans stopped exporting the vaccine
raw materials to india they said america
comes first that's what the biden
administration did they stopped
exporting
vaccine raw materials to india because
they said that america must come first
so hey
that's what's happening enjoy it
india's national interest will come
first the people of india will always
come first everything else comes later
that's how it goes and that's how the
world has always
rolled
and that's how we are doing that that's
how that's what we are doing we are
putting our own interests first uh
yesterday i released this
video about the jaishankar doctrine one
of the tenets of the jejunka doctrine is
that our interests come first
your interests come later we are going
to engage with the world on on the basis
of shared interests
and mutual respect so when people are
criticizing india why there is no
respect so if you don't want to respect
us you don't expect anything from us
that's how it goes
so
that's just how it's going to be people
can criticize people can people can
cry and moan
they can keep doing it it doesn't matter
india will
ensure that its own national interest is
first and that's how it's going to go
so that's why india has banned wheat
exports
for now
yash says recently the government of
india has ordered vpn service providers
to keep logs for five years
is this decision good or bad will this
affect a normal vpn user who doesn't use
vpn for illegal activities
it will affect
nobody who doesn't use who doesn't
indulge in any illegal activity nothing
at all nothing will change for you your
life will go on just as it is always go
on nothing will change for you
at the back end whatever happens you
were never aware of it anyway now you
heard something
makes no difference to your daily life
and how do you know that these vpn
providers were not already logging
everything and keeping the records or
logs for whatever years
all of these companies they share data
with the government
have you ever heard of prism
uh i think uh more than a decade ago
this prism mass surveillance program
came to light when edward snowden
defected from the u.s to russia and he
uh
revealed to the world how the americans
are collecting data of all kinds
from
people in other countries from all
across the world because they have this
monopoly on social media on the internet
on all that and that's why they're able
to collect metadata granular data they
know exactly what you think they know
where you've been they know what sites
you visit good sites bad sites whatever
they know exactly what's going on in
your life
they may even understand you better than
you understand yourself and that was 10
12 years ago and just imagine how it is
today so all of your data is already
being logged
but it's being logged by not your
government but by foreign governments
right so now the government of india has
or has
implemented institut instituted this new
policy
in which vpn service providers will keep
logs and share them with the government
on demand
well that's good
see this concept of privacy it's it's
it's an illusion it's a there is no such
thing as privacy online
you have
a track
you have a record everything you have
done on online is essentially logged
somewhere there is no such thing like
privacy
the west likes to talk about privacy and
all that but uh it is the worst
breaker of privacy in the world
so the thing so what's a vpn let's talk
about what a vpn is vpn is virtual
private network essentially
it allows you it if you buy a vpn
service it means that your service
provider vpn provider will uh
it will allow you to hide your ip
address and location whenever you are
browsing
the internet or going to any website so
they will not the website if it is using
cookies or whatever place you're
visiting
your uh tracks will be kind of covered
your actual ip address will be masked
and you will have better data encryption
so well let's say you have
a
vpn you have bought a vpn service it's
installed on your phone and you are in a
public location you're using public
wi-fi and you want to do a bank
transaction so if your location is
exposed
if your ip address is exports then then
there's a higher higher chance of of
your
bank account getting
getting hacked so if you use a vpn that
kind of that provides you extra layers
of security
so that
is still going to be there the only
thing is that vpn is no longer going to
be anonymous or or private it actually
no longer was there is this
famous
email provider called protonmail
they their usp unix service unique
service proposition unique selling
proposition usp was that it was
completely private and they do not care
they did not keep any records of
what you do
and yet eventually it was revealed that
they were keeping track and keeping
records of what people were doing
so their entire usp was a lie
so that's how it always has been
there is no such thing as privacy online
so you just need to
deal with it and get used to it and the
reason why the government of india is is
or has is
implementing this policy is to
to crack down on cyber fraud and cyber
terrorism and actual terrorism
so it's possible that certain
terrorist elements may use vpn services
to mask their
footprint online and and communicate
securely with other terrorists in other
parts of the
well
of the surface of the planet
so if
these logs are kept then the government
of india will be able to crack down upon
them will be able to track them and
apprehend them and maybe even prevent
crimes and terrorism it will also
ensure that
the incidence of cyber crime bank fraud
scams etc all of that comes down so
actually it's a very good thing
the government of india is doing this in
the pursuit of the national interest and
i think we should all support that so
please uh
understand that there is no such such
thing as privacy online you may think
what you're doing is private
someone knows about it
or some machine some algorithm knows
about it and it categorizes and
classifies you according to your
behavior online so be aware of that
please
okay rakshit says
in the us we see black people demanding
rights and equality and want to
acknowledge the atrocities
by european settlers but why don't we
see native americans doing the same this
is a very good question
so let us understand that
uh
the white settlers the european settlers
did
perpetrated un untold incredible
atrocities
on two
ethnicities the black people and the
natives the natives the native americans
are the true
owners of the land
the entire continent of north america
actually belongs to the native americans
it has been theirs for thousands of
years
the white europeans these settlers they
came in in the last 500 or so years only
they
usurped the land that stole the land and
carried out a
horrific genocide of the natives
and also
what they did was they enslaved the
black people whom they
imported from africa like goods
so this
the entire
success of north america two nations
america us usa and canada is built upon
it is built upon the genocide of the
native americans in the enslavement of
the african-americans
so the black people also have been
subjected to horrific atrocities there
is absolutely no denying that and today
i'm glad to see that this has
uh
this is being recognized today and black
lives do matter now i mean if you even
look at the
track record of the u.s in the last 50
years it's been horrible if you are a
black person
then you have a much higher probability
of being shot for no reason by the cops
this is a fact
so these days black lives matter has
become a thing and black people are
being more represented in the media and
the tv
uh
in you know overall
social life and all that which is good
but to some extent it's all pretense
because
they even now the black people the
african-americans they don't have their
own political party which which looks
out for their interests
why isn't there a political party that
looks out for the interests of the
african-american american people it's
not there
everything is force fitted in two
parties into two parties the republicans
are the democrats and these are the
democrats claim that they represent all
the minority rights and all that which
is very nice to know
and yet like you point out
nothing is being done
to acknowledge the genocide of the of
the native americans the native
americans are still marginalized
they are still treated like second-class
citizens there is still this horrific
epidemic of missing
women
when a native american woman goes
missing or a girl goes missing nothing
is done about it
typically the cops don't even take any
action
and they are they're still forced to
live on these
reservations you know segregated ghettos
uh so so that's the kind of
treatment that is still
meted out to the native americans
and they are still marginalized in the
21st century
so what's truly happening is that the
political class of the us
is using
the issue of black rights and and black
atrocities
for political gains
that's what it is doing so it is good
that the
plight of the black people of the
african-american people is now being
highlighted it is a very good thing
but why
is the same not happening for the native
americans they are still marginalized so
that is the hypocrisy of the west
they don't they it is still a racist
society it is still a highly unequal in
unequal society
it is still a society in which certain
sections of the society are marginalized
they are still
demonized in some ways stay don't get
off reservation that's what hillary
clinton said once in the during the 2016
presidential campaign don't get off the
reservation that is a racist
phrase so the us and the west is still a
very racist place you can see that
happening in real time
in eastern europe
all of that came out in the open
when the war began in ukraine you could
see how the the amount of racism that
african students and indian students had
to face
so that is not just characteristic of
eastern europe it's spread all across
the west these attitudes they were
kept below the surface for a very long
time but the the attitudes were always
there
the undercurrent of racism has always
been there in the western world
so you see that
in this case the native americans are
still completely marginalized they're
still second-class citizens and no one
cares
that's how it is so that is the
hypocrisy
of these so-called progressive liberal
types
they are
progressive and liberal only when it
comes to certain certain sections of the
society not to all
they don't treat everyone equally that
is the textbook definition of racism
and inequality
okay umkar says
who are the original inhabitants of
australia in new zealand what was their
culture like
excellent question let's take a look at
the map because as you know i am a very
big fan of the map so let's go there
so as you can see
this is india
right you can see where india is if you
go south
and east from india you reach australia
and further east from australia you have
new zealand which is essentially two big
islands and a few smaller ones
in australia includes the big landmass
the continent of australia and tasmania
which is an island to the south
of new so off of victoria
so that is australia and that is new
zealand the original inhabitants let's
talk let's take australia first
the original inhabitants of australia
are the australian aboriginal people the
native
australians and they have inhabited this
continent
for about at least i would say 60 000
years uh you can look up the exact
amount of years the exact
dating online but roughly about 60 000
years at least they have lived
on the continent of australia
so uh
so the native
australians the aboriginal australians
are the original inhabitants and the
true
uh owners of the continent of australia
the white
colonization the european colonization
of australia began just about two and a
half centuries before today
approximately
about two two and a half centuries
before today before that there were no
white people no europeans in australia
and today as you can as you can all see
the uh
native australians there's australian
aborigines have been completely
marginalized their land the best parts
of australia have been stolen from them
they are
segregated
more or less as you can see that the
nice parts of australia the coastal
parts
essentially the eastern and southern
coast of australia which is the
uh parts of australia with good climate
and greenery etc they have all been
taken over by the colonizers by the
colonialists by the settlers
in the arid inhospitable terrain of
australia is where you can still see
some
native australians living places like
alice springs for instance
where you have significant native
australian presence and various other
places
right cairns darwin
and various other places
so
they were the the australian aborigines
are the original inhabitants of
australia about five thousand years
before today
you will see that there was an
introgression of indian genetics into
the native australian population
so today the australian or the native
australians the australian aboriginal
people
have about between five to ten percent
indian ancestry
it's because of a voyage made by ancient
indians about 5000 years before today to
australia and they clearly settled down
over there and intermingled and
intermarried with the natives
and that also brings uh introduced the
australian wild dog the dingo into
australia which is essentially the
nothing but the
indian dog species
so that is about australia when it comes
to new zealand new zealand is believed
to be complete to have been
uninhabited free of human settlement
until about eight or nine hundred years
before today
so about eight or 900 years before today
the uh polynesian peoples called the
maoris
settled down in new zealand so the
true inhabitants the true owners of new
zealand are the maori people
and then you have the same thing as in
australia the european colonialists
came to new zealand
they
had these this conflict with the maori
people not the maori people
are a war like people
so there was this violent conflict with
the europeans but eventually the maori
is lost
they were subjugated
and the land was against stolen from
them
and today i think the maori people
constituted between 15 to 17 of the
total population of new zealand
everybody else is of essentially from
the british islands
white people european english-speaking
people most of the others and even among
those
15 16 of the
people who are of maori ethnicity
only about
one-fifth of them can actually speak
some form of the maori language so of
the entire population of new zealand
only about three percent of the people
three percent can speak the maori
language everybody else speaking speaks
english so as you can see
the maori culture has been wiped out
the maori language is close to
extinction
the land has been stolen from the
natives and they are marginalized today
and there are there is a much higher
rate of crime and homelessness and drug
addiction and alcohol abuse and all that
among the maori people compared to the
white people
and similarly for australia the
aboriginal people have a much much uh
lower life expectancy and much higher
incidence of substance abuse and all
kinds of other problems they are also
treated like the like the way the
african-americans are treated in
north america
the cops are much more likely to to
shoot them or to
imprison them on no charges etc
so that's how it is a very racist
society a very brutal society the true
inhabitants are marginalized the culture
of the native australians is a very
peaceful gentle culture it is one with
nature
it kind of recognizes nature as the
mother as a sacred as divine
polytheistic culture
so
that's how it is
in in some ways there are some parallels
with indian culture
so that is about the original
inhabitants of australia
and new zealand and their culture
himanki says how can india take its
revenge
for all the humiliations it faced from
the turks and the europeans
the best form of revenge
is success
so
that's it
india needs to succeed indian industry
needs to rise again
india is not an emerging nation india is
not an emerging economy it is a
re-emerging economy and nature in a
nation and civilization so the best form
of revenge is for india to rise to its
full potential
and reclaim its original historical
position in the global sphere
essentially is an economic cultural
civilizational
and military superpower
and as the pioneer as the as the nation
that is at the forefront of science and
technology
it is quite dispiriting to see people
disparage science that science is wrong
come on india invented science
so what india needs to do is india needs
to rise
india needs to become
prosperous successful and powerful that
is the best revenge then everything will
will fall into place
so that's what i can say
okay two questions from dungar singh
johan any updates on the james webb
telescope and can the james webb
telescope help us understand
anything about umuah
okay
the james webb space telescope in case
some of you may not know is a new
space telescope that has been launched
it was launched uh in december at the
end of december last year 2021
and it has uh after a journey of a month
or so it reached its destination in
space at the uh i think the l3 lagrange
point
which it will orbit
and it's going to peer deep into space
it is an improved it's a much bigger
a space telescope compared to the hubble
space telescope the mirror is much
larger
and it operates primarily in the
infrared domain
and
it will essentially function as a
time machine it will peer further back
and further far away into space than the
hubble space telescope ever could have
done
so it's a much more powerful space
telescope and uh the instruments have
all been calibrated more or less
calibrated by now initially the each of
the segments the hexagonal segments of
the mirror was producing a different
distinct image of each star
but now they have all been focused
together the the alignment is done
and it is more or less
it has almost reached its uh operating
temperature which is like on very close
to absolute zero
so it's almost ready it's already taking
images the images are coming out very
good so it is almost ready i think we
could uh start start seeing the first
science data within a month or two at
most
so we are already in the middle of may
i think most likely within
the next month or so we should be able
to see the first
science uh
data coming in from the from the
james webb telescope space telescope so
that is the status as of now
very exciting
so can the james webb space telescope
help us understand anything about um not
quite
it is not a telescope that is designed
to focus on a narrow point in space
so if you want to
uh
if you want to study um with a telescope
you would have to focus on a very narrow
point in space right so what is um it is
uh
it is
what looks like
a space rock
of some kind which essentially is now
known to have come from outer space
it is not something that was part of the
solar system it came from outside the
solar system it passed through it
went around the sun in a
hyperbolic orbit
i'm not sure if
it was hyperbolic or parabolic most
likely hyperbolic and it's now going
back out into outer space it will never
come back again as far as we know
so uh
and there has been some speculation that
it it may have been an artificial object
because
uh the amount of of light it was
reflecting was kind of excessive
and it seemed
to change its speed
like acceleration kind of thing you know
which is not normal for a space rock
so some people have speculated or
claimed that it is a an artificial
object
maybe some kind of probe that came into
the solar system
so uh
so yeah that's the claim that we made
and uh
there is no real way right now of
studying it because it's so small and
it's already so far away it may be
possible to catch up with it if we
launch
a spacecraft this year or maybe the next
year then maybe one could be able to
catch up with it in the next decade or
decade and a half possibly in that case
we would be able to uh study it but the
james webb telescope is not designed to
focus on a very narrow point in space
its focus to it is designed to focus on
a large on large areas of space and
collect lots of data and information
so uh
so i don't expect the james webb space
telescope to be used for studying
umuamua there will be planetary science
done with this with this telescope
solar system objects will be
investigated because many of our solar
system objects they
emit radiation in the in the
infrared wavelengths
so yeah in that case we will
get some new information but not in the
case of
um bruh bruh says what is the bretton
woods system
let me just take a look at the live chat
is there any issue with the
with the image i think it's all fine
all right
so the question is what is the britain
woods system
the bretton woods system is the economic
system that was created by the
victorious powers of
the second european tribal war which is
better known as world war ii
so
the victorious powers
in the second world war
was actually the victorious power which
is the united states
so the united states created this
bretton woods system along with its uh
allies
the victoria the the the countries that
were on the victorious side
and it is called the brittonville system
because it there was a conference which
took place at two or three week
conference that took place in the
bretton woods hotel in the u.s
so what was done is that
as part of the system this part of the
agreement
the us dollar
was institutionalized as the global
reserve currency
it was pegged to gold i think 35 dollars
an ounce or something like that look it
up i'm not sure
most likely that that sort of price
so the us dollar was institutionalized
as the proxy for gold and it was made
the default international currency
that's the first thing of the that's the
first uh pillar
of the bretton woods system
and also two uh
institutions were created they created
the imf and the world bank
so these are two institutions that still
exist today the ostensible aim of these
institutions was to
provide finances and support to
developing countries and countries which
were devastated in the second world war
and that sort of thing the imf and the
world bank which still exist today
so the dollar became the default reserve
international currency it was pegged to
the price of gold
so this
agreement happened in 1944 i think and
it became fully operational in the late
1950s
so and until 19 until the 1970s the us
dollar remained pegged to gold
and then the u.s president richard nixon
kind of devalued the price of the dollar
of the
and eventually d-linked the dollar from
from gold from the price of gold so the
dollar became a free floating currency
it was no longer linked to gold and the
u.s could print as many dollars as they
wanted it actually eventually became the
petro dollar it became tied in a way to
the price of oil because
oil transaction transactions are all
mostly done nowadays in us dollars
so the bretton wood system kind of
collapsed in the 1970s and yet the
hegemony it created still exists the
american hegemony the entire global
financial system is more or less
predicated on the us dollar it is
based in the u.s dollar so which gives
the united states enormous leverage
globally
economic leverage
it can impose sanctions in any country
which cuts the country off from the u.s
dollar which means the country cannot
transact anything with the
rest of the world without paying very
heavy prices
and
the imf the world bank also they are
instruments of essentially western or
u.s hegemony
and so on so the bretton wood system
even though it collapsed in the 1970s it
created
the american economic hegemony that we
still see today so it all began in 1944
in the
end stage of the second world war so
that in brief is about the britain woods
system
samarth says what should be india's
position on this on on south korea's
desire
to join the quad
let it join the quad
let's make it a quintet
no longer the quad a quintet
you know what
let's examine what the quad is
let's go to the map
and take a look at the quad countries
which are the countries that constitute
the quad
you have the united states
you have australia australia
you have japan
and you have india four countries
constitute the quad now the u.s is the
global superpower
australia
is a u.s corporation or a u.s colony
japan
is under u.s military occupation since
it is a u.s vasal state
only india
has an independent foreign policy so you
have india and three nations which are
either the u.s or extensions of the u.s
so it is essentially an indo-us
collaboration of some kind
that's what the quad is
now the objective of the quad obviously
is to counter balance china india
obviously will feel threatened by the
rise of china china has in the
historically shown it's that it is not
reliable that it seeks to break india
that it uh sees india as a threat
it does not seek india to do well
and china is obviously a very large
economy like five times that of india
today in terms of overall gdp
and it has a correspondingly much larger
military strength so obviously india
would want to align with other nations
ally or or partner with other nations in
order to counter balance china the us is
obviously alarmed at the rise of china
so it also wants to use india
as a counterweight in asia to china
and why not go in with the other wasal
states like australia and japan because
australia also feels certainly
threatened by china by the rise of china
the chinese have infiltrated deep into
australia their tentacles are deep into
australian politics into the australian
economy and various walks of life so the
australians are really alarmed about the
rise of china there is this new
development the solomon islands have
inked a pact with china which
has military dimensions so you could
have chinese missiles at australia's
doorstep like the like the cuban missile
crisis in the 1960s that sort of
situation
and obviously japan also is alarmed
about the rise of china because the
chinese
seek to destabilize and eventually
hopefully
possibly destroy japan
right
so all of these nations see china as a
threat rightfully so
and that's why these four countries are
together
in this quadrilateral
dialogue it's called right
now south korea also has
well it doesn't have very good relations
historically with china
uh north korea is a china chinese
satellite state
south korea is a u.s vasal state it is
under military occupation by the u.s
since the 1950s
permanent u.s military occupation so
south korea itself
is like an extension of the u.s just
like japan and australia are u.s all
states similarly china uh south korea is
also a us was our state so whether south
korea officially comes into the quad or
not it doesn't make much of a difference
it will anyway
do whatever the us tells it to do it is
an instrument
of the us
so whether it is officially part of the
quad or not it is anyway on the side of
the quad
in the same boat
as the quad so as far as india is
concerned uh it doesn't really make much
of a difference obviously there are
things like optics and diplomacy and all
that if south korea joins the quad then
it it looks like the quad is embarking
on an expansion the way nato expanded in
the
in europe
and that might be seen by the chinese as
some kind of provocation so maybe it may
not be the best idea for south korea to
join the court anyway
it makes no difference because south
korea is anyway an extension of the us
and as such is in the same boat
and therefore even if it is not actually
officially part of the quad its policies
will be any way aligned with those of
the quad so it really makes no
difference
in the real world
okay lone wolf says
thank you for this video the pacifist
ideology was the reason why many years
ago
i rejected the indian part of my
ancestry i am mixed race my mother is
100 indian i had in fact in fact
presumed that my mother's ancestors were
weak links and nothing to be proud of so
it's music to my ears to find that my
ancestors did in fact have a warrior
spirit
i would like to find out more about
their warrior culture who were the
greatest indian warriors what their
stories and deeds
where can i find this information what
is a good starting point unfortunately i
don't speak my ancestors language and
can only read
uh english translations at the present
so yeah many people believe that india
is a nation of weak links that's what we
have all been taught that's the kind of
that's the kind of image that has been
projected by indian and western
historians india's historians are
essentially popular of the west
they have always told the western line
there is no new real research coming out
of india since the past 70 plus years
so yeah there is this this image of
indians as weaklings
i myself used to dislike reading indian
history because it was so
dispiriting and depressing all full of
defeats and all until i discovered the
real industry so the depressing part is
just the past 1000 years which i call
the
which i call india's millennium of
humiliation before that india was the
greatest civilization in the world it is
the oldest continuously existing
civilization the world has ever known
and
india was
a military
uh
was a country of military excellence
as we know the truth the cholas
conquered southeast asia all the way to
the philippines right
maritime conquest
uh the guptas
conquered uh
reconquered afghanistan and parts of
central asia lalita mukta peda conquered
large parts of central asia even some
parts of present-day xinjiang the
koshans
had uh
their their empire stretched from the
caspian sea to the sea and it included
the river basin part which is most of
today's present day xinjiang region of
china and so on and so forth um
the yamnia invaders of england of europe
who completely transformed the genetics
of europe where of indian origin and so
on and so forth so uh unfortunately the
problem is that you will not find
much most of these things that are just
mentioned you won't find them in any
history textbook
our history textbooks want to
portray a very
weak and pacifist kind of image of india
that stems from the ideology of mohandas
gandhi who
kept on insisting on turning the other
cheek and never fight back
so unfortunately
most text books whether they are written
by foreign authors or indian authors do
not mention any of this in any detail uh
if you want to learn about
the kushan conquests
and the the gupta empire etc
even the chula empire
one of the good sources is the
is the author rc majumdar who
essentially wrote his books nearly a
century ago and yet so so much of the
information
at least some of the information is kind
of outdated and yet there are excellent
reference books for those portions of
indian history
and
what
what i have done is i have
researched i've read research papers
journal articles etc from which i got
much of my information but i can't
really think of any other textbook or
history book apart from the books by rc
madonna
that go into any detail about these
periods of indian history
but most of the information is is
available online in different places you
have to be judicious in
judging whether the information you are
reading is correct or not because some
of these are just blog posts obviously
blog posts are not authoritative
i would say read research papers
research articles from
peer-reviewed journals
etc from and
if you can yeah so that would be a good
starting point and yeah
so that's what i can say but uh this
entire image of india as is a nation of
weaklings
as a nation with this ideology of losers
the ideology of mohandas gandhi that is
a false image india was entirely
different
india
was a nation of saints and scholars
and also warriors and also farmers
everybody was there everybody
contributed equally i mean you can't
have a great civilization without equal
contributions from all walks of life and
you had that in india india was the
greatest maritime seafaring civilization
of all time and you will not see this
being mentioned anywhere
i mean how did the cholas
conquer all the way
to the philippines how did the people of
kalinga
in culturate southeast asia uh
almost two thousand years before the
cholas and so on so there's a lot that
is not taught but it's all nowadays
available online you just need to
learn to look
for the information in the right places
so all the best to you sir
okay bro again
do you think russia's foreign policy
revolves around mackinder's heartland
thesis
some policy experts believe that the
multi-polar world which india and russia
seek is an unstable world what are your
thoughts on that
in order for india's plans against the
chinese tibet plays a vital role
how do you think
what do you think could be changed
where 50 of the tibetan population is
today uh han chinese actually today more
than 50 of the population of tibet is
han chinese the chinese have completely
transformed the demographics of tibet
the han chinese the chinese speaking
people are now a majority in tibet that
tibetans are now a minority in their own
land in their own country
so that's where we are anyway uh
do i think russia's foreign policy
revolves around machinder's heartland
thesis good question so what is
mcinder's heartland thesis
so makinder was a
british i think british historian
as far as remember most likely british
so he came across he came
he uh proposed this theory or this
thesis
which is called the heartland thesis
which says that the
power that controls
eurasia and africa
is going to control the world and rule
the world
so according to his theory
europe asia and africa are the heartland
of the world island
and the outer islands or outer lands are
the north and south america and
australia and the other islands so
according to magic mechandr the power
that controls eurasia
and africa is going to rule the world
and the heartland the actual heartland
is north of the himalayas all the way up
to siberia
and west of the volga i think and east
of the yangtze
so this entire region of eurasia north
of the himalayas
between eastern europe
and uh
eastern asia is the actual heartland of
the world
and according to makinder the nation or
the power that controls the heartland is
going to rule the world and of course
you have mayhem's thesis that which is
the rimland thesis which says that the
maritime powers will rule the world so
whichever nation can control the seas
the oceans of the world is going to
control the world so these are two
competing hypotheses these are still
theories nobody has actually tested them
out there has never been an instance in
the entire history of the world where
any power controls the entire heartland
of uh
of eurasia
so
russia obviously as you know occupies
much of the heartland
of makinder
so yes it will obviously console it it
will seek to consolidate its power in
that region
the chinese are
embarking upon a new world strategy
of trying to control the rim land which
is the oceans the trade routes
and also parts of the heartland via the
belt and road uh initiative the
bri
so uh yeah these are two powers that
seek to control
various parts of the world and obviously
as we know the americans
are the dominant power in western europe
parts of northern europe they are trying
to expand eastwards
and they are also the dominant power in
the oceans
but there has never been a time in the
entire history world that one power has
controlled the entire heartland what uh
mackinder defined as the heartland
so i don't think russia's foreign policy
revolves around the heartland thesis
uh
they wish to stop nato's expansion and
they also wish to in the long run
counter balance china in some way they
have to rise again for that so that is
in short what russia's foreign policy is
long-term foreign policy is likely to be
uh some policy experts believe a
multi-polar world will be unstable well
that's just a hypothesis how do we know
it will be unstable maybe it will be
more stable maybe it will be a much more
fairer and egalitarian world
a world with less
hegemony from one one source
so uh
so yeah it's is very people can believe
anything but what's the evidence that
it's going to be like that there is no
such evidence
experts have opinions even non-experts
have opinions you know what they say
about opinions right everyone has one it
doesn't make any difference
this this uh
belief or opinion is not really based on
any actual data
so it's just an opinion it doesn't
really matter
and uh
tibet plays a vital role the han
population is over 50 in tibet what can
india do right india can do nothing
right now
uh
someday if we are able to liberate tibet
then we will think about it about that
when we come to the
point in history right now there's no
point thinking about that
imperial says
should states in our country be
subordinates of the center or should
they have some autonomy to maintain the
so-called federal structure what is this
federal structure and why is it so
important
what's really important is the long term
national interest
so the national interest
is what we need to look look after
not some idea of india which
incorporates a federal structure or
whatever else it is
and
a nation
a civilization state like india which is
so large it is a subcontinent sized
civilization a nation of that scale
needs to be ruled from the center it
needs a very strong
central
authority the truth rules it
look at the past few thousand years of
indian history and think about the times
when india was the most prosperous
and the most powerful
each of these times india had a very
strong central government
that's how it has always been so
whenever india has done well it has had
a strong central government and no
so-called federal structure
and of course there has been
a self-rule at the level of the villages
and cities and towns
so there has always been some form of
democracy in india but an indian hybrid
form of democracy india has had
a an imperial system and localized
democracy
which which
essentially means that people can decide
how they're going to live and how
they're going to govern themselves at
the local level so that is what is best
suited for india
states i think have too much autonomy
too many states go in directions that
are actually inimical to the indian
national interest
i'm not naming any specific state but we
can see examples today
of that happening in real time
so i think states have too much power
there is too much so-called democracy in
india like the chinese are fond of
saying
so states
first of all um
one should also be open to the idea to
have more states some states are
enormous 300 million plus population
some states have a population of 2
million
we should have states that are of
approximately similar size
and the smaller a state is going to be
or a smaller
an administrative unit is going to be
the better governed it is going to be
because there will be more proximity for
each person for each citizen to the
government
so uh eventually some restructuring of
india needs to happen what really
matters in the long run is the overall
long-term national interest
not these little petty disputes between
states and
more autonomy for states and all that
states have too much autonomy right now
too many of them go in directions that
are very there are not good for the
national interest so this
needs to be revisited at the right time
not yet
okay
says would it have been better if
mikhail gorbachev was the first
president of russia instead of boris
yeltsin
although many people blame gorbachev for
the disintegration of the ussr he had
realized the fact
that the ussr needed some political and
economic changes if gorbachev was the
first president would the shock therapy
have been less intensive
and russia being comparatively less
turmoil and could it also have changed
the political the present political
scenario let's understand what really
happened
the russians consider gorbachev to be a
traitor
they regard him as
a western puppet as an agent of the us
so he introduced in the 1980s these
changes
you said that he realized that ussr
needed some political economic changes
why
these changes destroyed the nation
he instituted perestroika and glasnost
opening up and self-criticism and
admission of guilt and what not it made
the ussr look weak it made the
government look weak
every government has shortcomings every
government has failings you think the us
government did not have any shortcomings
and fails at the time
but they never admitted any of the
shortcomings but gorbachev
embarked upon this crusade of
self-criticism of perestroika of
glasnost of revealing what's wrong with
the ussr and of allowing more autonomy
and allowing free speech there is
nothing as a free speech actually you
know that
anyway so he did all those things and
the actions that it took in the 1980s
they culminated they resulted in the
disintegration of the ussr
right so he destroyed
the nation that his predecessors had
built he destroyed essentially the
empire
his predecessors had built that's what
he did
so his
job was done
his job was done he he became the
darling of the west he still is the
darling of the west he is still a word
of wisdom a word of reason he is still
critical of the way russia is run today
so it's it's quite
clear that there is some truth
some truth some some element of truth in
this allegation that he is in he was in
some way
pro-west or possibly even an agent of
the west
so his job
was to destroy the ussr his job was done
and then he was sidelined and then a new
job had to be done
so out of the ussr came out one big
entity which was russia
now russia was still extremely powerful
extremely powerful of the huge economy
and a powerful state machinery
and a fully industrialized nation
and the industries were in the hands of
the
or the state of the government
so
that's where boris yeltsin comes in
bori silson uh played a major role in
the so-called
disintegration of the ussr not the
so-called the actual disintegration of
the ussr
he was part of the protests he jumped on
he climbed a tank and posed in front of
the western media and so on and
eventually he became the first president
of russia
and what he did
during his presidency apart from drink
copious amounts of alcohol what he did
was
he destroyed
the russian economy thoroughly
see it's like this
russia the ussr was a communist state
the union of soviet socialist republics
all property was collectivized
the nation's wealth was collectivized
the its its custodian was the communist
party but the wealth the industries
and all property belong to the people
and the entire gdp everything the ussr
had built up had been built by the labor
of the people
so when russia became emerge out of the
ussr everything that
that was present in russia the
industries the land the the money the
foreign reserves everything it belonged
to the people it was the result of
decades of labor done by the people now
what this fellow yeltsin did
is that
he privatized everything
and he placed russia's industries
in the hands of a few
crooked people
who are now called the oligarchs
right
and he ensured that he appointed the
worst people to run all these industries
and
oh in just
in a period of just a few years
all of these industries were essentially
bankrupted
so the first thing he did was he took
all of the money that was the fruit of
decades of labor of the russian people
and he placed all that money in the in
the pockets
of a few corrupt
people
he stole all the money
all the money was stolen
the people's money was stolen and it
became
the property of these corrupt oligarchs
and secondly the oligarchs proceeded to
destroy thoroughly the russian economy
and destroy the industries of russia and
they parked away enormous amounts of
money in the west
right
all these russian oligarchs have
properties in the west in london etc and
much of the money is still sitting there
so that was the role that boris yeltsin
played he was also
essentially an agent of the west
so he was suited suited for this role of
destroying the russian economy gorbachev
was more suitable to destroy the ussr
so they both played their role it's only
after vladimir putin came to power that
he stopped the bleeding and started
rebuilding russia and that's why
the second cold war started and it's
it's now slowly becoming a hot war
so i don't think gorbachev should have
been i mean gorbachev did his job of
destroying the ussr and yeltsin did his
job of destroying russia
and it's only because of an accident
that someone like putin came to power
and he turned out to be the guy who
slowly transformed the fortunes of
russia
so uh so that's what i have to say about
this
okay anime says what can we learn from
the strategy putin
used in chatsharya
how was he able to crush the terrorism
can we do anything of that sort in
kashmir okay let's understand chechnya
what happened there
first of all
when it comes to chechnya the people of
chechnya have an enormous amount of
respect for vladimir putin
the the
president is it of chechnya
kadhirov
ramzan kadeer of the son of ahmad
kabhirov so the current president of
chechnya who is essentially the de facto
king of chechnya is ramzan kadyrov if
you go to his house
if you go to his palace
you will see two enormous portraits
in the main room
in the hall
one of these enormous portraits is ahmad
khadirov ramzan khaderov's father and
the second portrait is that of
so essentially ramzan khadirov treats
vladimir putin
on par with his own father right and he
is completely and utterly loyal to
vladimir putin
and the chechens
are now completely loyal to russia they
are now fighting in ukraine on behalf of
russia
a significant portion of the russian
military comes from chechnya because
chechnya is one place where the birth
rate is is is greater than the death
rate so the population is growing over
there
but it was not always the case
there was a time when chechnya tried to
secede from the ussr from russia itself
after the disintegration of the ussr
chechnya was part of russia
now they wanted to become an independent
country they actually declared
independence in the 1990s the russians
tried to reintegrate chichnia through
military means under boris yeltsin
the first chechnyan war chechen war
happened in the mid-90s look up the
dates
i don't memorize dates it was in the
mid-90s and the russians lost
the first chechen war
there was a disaster for russia
military disaster
then after vladimir putin came to power
the first thing he did more or less the
first thing he did it was
it was on the top of his list of
priorities
he embarked upon the second chechen war
and
he crushed the resistance
the russian military crushed the
resistance
and chechnya was
reintegrated into russia
through
brute force
it was like
they pulverized flattened chechnya
it was brute force overwhelming force
and it was bloody and it was brutal
so
what
putin did was that he cultivated certain
elements of the chechen
so-called freedom struggle
who turned who turned their allegiance
and became allies of russia
one of them was ahmad khadirov
who became the
the i think he became the president
after the war was over he was
assassinated and then his son became the
president
or whatever the title is of the head of
the of the republic
so uh
what
putin did
is that he spoke to these chechens in a
language they understood
there is the language of power the
language of force brute force
some see every culture is different
there is nothing right or wrong about
any culture there is nothing especially
good or bad
from a certain perspective you can see
it like that
so in some cultures people respect
wisdom
knowledge
refinement
civilization
in some cultures people respect
brute force and strength
so in the case of chechnya it's like
they respect strength they respect brute
force and putin showed that he will be
respected he is worthy of respect
so the chechens respect him today so
that's what he did he was able to crush
the terrorism
with an iron fist he smashed the
resistance out of chechnya that's what
it did we should not do that in kashmir
the kashmiris are our own people they
some of some elements may be there
in currently in kashmir which may be pro
pakistan or whatever that will be taken
care of in due time
we should not use the chechnya bottle in
kashmir we are
well
we should we have a different way of
doing things i'm sure we can do it in
our own way
without resorting to uh overwhelming
force or anything
we should
see the people of kashmir are our own
brothers and sisters they're the same
blood as us some of them may be
misguided we will
re-guide them right so that's what we
should do we should not uh
employ military means
or brute force tactics
okay
saurabh says what is the script of the
methane kingdom how was this script
deciphered which had vedic names
what is their native language and what
was the form of sanskrit found there
vedic or post vedic
um okay yeah that's essentially the gist
of the question
so let's go into what um
the mithani kingdom or bhitani empire so
let's go to the map once again
i'm sure you all know where india is
this is india let's go westwards
inch by inch inch by inch
this is uh temporarily the country of
pakistan then you have gandhara which is
now called afghanistan you go further
west you come to the land of the parsha
people the persians the iranians
you go further west you come to iraq
mesopotamia
and further west is anatolia so the
mithani kingdom or methane empire
flourished in this region present-day
iraq syria and anatolia
about three and a half thousand
years before today roughly roughly okay
plus or minus
a couple of centuries
and it was in power for about 350 years
three and a half centuries or so
so that is the mithani kingdom its
capital was vashokhani which means in
sanskrit the mind of treasure
so uh that was
the methane kingdom
empire
now what was the script that they used
what was the language they spoke so
first of all let's talk about the
language the language that the people of
this empire or kingdom spoke
was the horyan language which was which
is an extinct language it was i think
not
an indo-european language it was
uh it belonged to a local language
family
which is now no longer extent
so that is the language that the people
spoke the majority of the population but
the aristocracy the royalty spoke a
different language they spoke sanskrit
not persian they spoke sanskrit
and what form of sanskrit did they speak
they spoke late vedic sanskrit not
pre-vedic or vedic sanskrit but late
vedic sanskrit so the sanskrit language
has evolved over the thousands of years
vedic sanskrit the kind of script you
find in the rigveda is different from
the sanctity you find in the later
vedas
so the sanskrit these people the the
royalty the aristocracy of the muthani
kingdom spoke was late vedic sanskrit
and we know because certain words that
they used were not found in
early vedic sanskrit one of the best
examples is the word for night
so
the early vedic word
for for night night time
today today what is the sanskrit word
for night it is
right
that's the word that we can use in any
indian language
so that is the word we use today for
night time raktri
so that was the word that was used in
sanskrit for night time in the late
vedic phase
but in the early vedic phase during the
rigvedic phase
there was a different word
and at that time the word for night was
the
next n-a-k-t
and that is where
that is the word from where the english
word night
comes from the latin word nokte comes
from it comes from the vedic sanskrit
word nakta
but later a new word came in which was
ratri which is what we use now
so the mithani royalty aristocracy spoke
late vedic sanskrit not early vedix
which means that they were from a time
period
much later than the time period of the
rigveda that clearly shows that right
so that tells you clearly that the
rigvedas have been written a long time
before
1500 bce
that's one of the ways of dating
approximately the rigveda roughly rough
dating right so the native language of
the aristocracy and the royalty
of the mithrani was late vedic sanskrit
they were migrants out of india they had
conquered this land and they were
administering and ruling it the natives
spoke the horyan language which was not
an indian or indo-iranian language it
was a different it belonged to a
different language family
so how do we know all this because we
have found inscriptions
there is one very famous inscription
it's a it's an entire horse training
manual
which can still be used today to train
horses it was written by a
a horse master whose name was cool
and he wrote this entire training manual
in the hurian language
but there were certain terms for which
there was no word in the korean language
and therefore he had to use sanskrit
terms for that so that's where we find
the first evidence of written sanskrit
so that's
so the script that was used for this in
this kingdom
was the cuny form script
uh
i think it was one of the assyrian
variants of the cuneiform script
as far as i know or was it the hittite
variant one of those variants of the
cuneiform script so how was the script
deciphered it took a long time
the
first attempts to decipher the cuneiform
script happened in the
1700s in the 18th century did not make
much progress then in the 1800s
in the first half of the century the
19th century
uh
people started started studying the
various inscriptions in cuneiform in
naksharostam
and the bahisto stone pakistan
inscription in persia
and slowly slowly by comparing it with
other other inscriptions etc and by
hypothesizing that it would sound like
sanskrit they were able to slowly crack
the script
so the hypothesis so these people who
were trying to study the script
had been to india
and they had le they knew about the
presence of parsi people in india you
know persian uh refugees who had come to
india and who were given shelter in
india quite magnanimously i would add
so they knew that uh
there were similarities between persian
and sanskrit
so they hypothesized that this script
would sound like sanskrit and it would
be more or less just like sanskrit in
using that hypothesis they were able to
slowly crack the script
and then they were able to find certain
uh
inscriptions in two or three languages
where they could compare
the the
the inscriptions and
verify whether their translation was
correct or not
and they also found some kind of pot or
something in egypt which had an
inscription in the uniform script and
also in egyptian hieroglyphics
which uh gave them further clues so it
took a few decades
but the script was eventually cracked
and they discovered that they were right
the ancient persian language of the
bhagavad-gana inscription of the uh
naksha-rustam inscription etc they
sounded just like sanskrit they
discovered that old person
from the haksha manish dynasty time 3000
years before today was essentially an
upper branch version of sanskrit
a
slightly corrupted version of sanskrit
so that is the story of this entire
matter good question sir
tushit says when foreign tourists come
to india
they go to very crowded and dirty places
like whatever in delhi and whatever in
mumbai
that's why people think india is a very
poor country filled with slums how can
we change this perception
well
the first thing is that slums do exist
in india
but you are right
foreigners especially from western
countries they love to visit slums
they do these slum tours in various
parts of india
especially in some big cities but you
have lots of slums
and one of the attractions for of for
them
for visiting india is to go and see
slums and see how people live in slums
and somehow they find it very
interesting
but
the fact is that slums do exist in india
today
i remember when i was a kid
i lived as a kid in europe for a few
years and as a kid a few years is like a
lifetime right
so when i first returned to india
the plane landed in one of the major
cities of india i will not name it
and on both sides of the highway
you had these slums
the plane is landing you can see slums
on both sides of the highway
huts terrible conditions and all these
non-indians they were taking photographs
out of the planes windows
so if we
and you know the thing is that
see i'm not naming any place
i'm sure there are many big cities in
india where you have slums
and at least in some of these places
these slums are deliberately kept in
place as vote banks by the local
politicians i'm not naming any city
please note that
but there are many places where this
happens
we have the resources and the
wherewithal to
eliminate all slums in india today
we can create proper housing and
construction and give people affordable
housing
so why can't we do it
some that's why i say that you know so
the states have too much around autonomy
many of the policies that certain states
are implementing and following
are inimical to the national interest
india today has enough money to
eradicate slums and homelessness forever
but we are still not doing it
so uh
this situation will continue as long as
as
the current system continues there is
unfortunately corruption in some places
there are certain politicians who
are self-serving in some places not i'm
not saying all some places right
and
certain states
a few i would imagine i can maybe you
can think of a couple of examples there
are some states where the policies are
not very good
so as long as this system continues the
self-serving system with karus with
which
which tolerates corrupt politicians then
these problems will continue and as long
as these problems continue we will have
slums and dirty places
and then
foreigners who enjoy
this sort of thing
they enjoy poverty tourism slum tourism
they will keep on doing this and the
image of india as a dirty poor country
will will be perpetuated
see how the chinese have transformed
their their reputation and their image
in the eyes of the world
they've been able to do it we can also
do it if we want to but i think it will
take time because the system is so
deeply entrenched
that i think it's going to be at least
another 10 20 years before we start
making significant changes
but it will happen it will
prashant says recently isro has
developed bricks to build structures on
mars
your views
where does india stand in the space race
ah israel is i'm not
i'm not sure if isro is developing brics
i heard some institutes in india
scientific cities in india were
developing bricks
so i find that about as interesting as a
cricket match between bangladesh and sri
lanka no disrespect to either of these
countries
that's the most boring thing ever
isro's job is not to build bricks
isro's job is to build the next
generation of space rockets and take
india forward into space
why waste money on building bricks you
can use any brick
on the moon on mars
that's not a big achievement if you have
developed a brick
if that is being done it's it's
unfortunate it's terrible it's very
underwhelming it's not some great
achievement that we should be proud of
developing bricks
breaks you can develop
you don't need a scientific
training to develop bricks
so isro's job is to
develop the next generation of
cutting-edge space technologies and
rockets
and space
stations and take india to the moon to
mars and further in the solar system and
establish india as a major
top three space power
that's what isro's job is i am not
criticizing the scientists the
scientists don't make decisions they do
as they are told it is the government
and the administrators of israel
who actually tell the scientists what to
do the scientists have no real autonomy
they simply follow orders so if they are
told to deploy to to develop bricks they
will develop bricks
that's how it is
where does india stand stand in the
space race
india has fallen behind in the space
race
decade ago india was was at the
forefront of the space race uh we had
sent a space probe to mars on the first
attempt not even the u.s was able to do
that
the only nation to successfully send a
spacecraft to mars in the first attempt
and that too on a shoestring budget that
demonstrated the incredible scientific
uh ability of india scientists and of
isro so that tells you what isro is
capable of that's that tells you the
kind of scientific scientific talent
that india has
but for the in the past few years
nothing has happened
we had this one chandrayaan
attempt in 2019
they should have sent a second
chandrayaan spacecraft six months later
and we are still still waiting for
chadraya when will it happen
right of the the chandrayaan orbiter
succeeded but the lander failed for
certain reasons i do not blame india
scientists for the failure of the lander
the lander was perfect something else
went wrong anyhow that's a different
story so
so india is not
at the forefront of the space race
anymore the chinese and the americans
are at the forefront
uh the last year
i think in the past two years since the
pandemic began we hardly had five or six
space launches from india
the chinese must have done over 100 the
americans have done well in excess of
100 in these past two years
space x itself
has launched 60 70 80 i'm not sure i
don't know maybe more than 100 rockets
so the pandemic did not stop or slow
down the americans or the chinese but
india
everything came to a halt
so india is kind of falling behind right
now which is extremely disappointing
extremely disappointing we have the
potential the talent the ability
to become the number one space power
and if you are at the forefront of space
you're going to be at the forefront of a
whole
wide variety of technologies which will
make you a global superpower
in the 21st century the two or three
nations that are at the forefront of
space exploration are going to be the
203 nations that rule the world
so india needs to
take this very seriously
once people start colonizing the mars
the moon and mars
there will not be enough space left
there for the other countries the
chinese
are making a beeline to the moon
so are the americans
in the next two to three years
by 25 2025 or 26
the americans plan to land
human beings on the moon again probably
by 24 i think
so uh they will
obviously want to establish a permanent
settlement on the moon the chinese also
want to do that
india should not get left behind
it's like uh
the exploration of the oceans all over
again
there is this new quest for new
territories to conquer
the next frontier is space it's the moon
it's mars india has to ensure it is not
left behind we have not even launched a
human being into space yet
so we need to get going with that right
now it is very disappointing but we have
the potential to become a space
superpower in a matter of a couple of
decades
so i hope
there are plans to to follow up on that
unwest says can we make it to mars as
far as elon musk's dream is concerned
what technological progress needs to be
done to establish a human settlement on
mars
as of today 2022 we have the technology
to send a human being to mars and bring
him or her back safely
but
the technology has not been
made foolproof and failure proof
completely so there is a significant uh
probability of failure
and it's okay if your rocket explodes or
if your spacecraft is lost but it's a
whole different thing if there's a
person on it
a human life
especially in space is a whole different
value
so the the
only thing that is stopping people right
now is
that there is a significant chance of
something going wrong
and you just don't want the the bad
optics of losing a human life right
so
we already have the technology even isro
can spend a spacecraft
to
mars using its
feeble underpowered rockets pslv which
is the tiny rocket
compared to
what uh spacex has or china has
so even isro can suspend
send a spacecraft to mars
and isro already has the technology
of a
of a space capsule that can support
human life
it's not been tested thoroughly yet but
we already have the technology we have
already built one
and we even tested some of it some of
the components
so uh the chinese
have been sending human beings into sp
into earth's orbit they have a small
space station
the russians are the technology the
americans of the technology so it can
already be we already have the
components and the technology to send
human beings to mars and possibly bring
them back alive
but uh
it has not yet been made completely
foolproof fail proof so i expect that
the first attempt on mars may happen
by the late 2020s or the mid 2030s at
the latest
and the most likely elon musk would be
the would want to be the person
to
do that
to launch
uh human beings via spacex
so
that's what i see happening
within a decade
may at max a decade and a half
okay gunpowder says we know that it's
almost impossible to travel travel
faster than the speed of light
so are there other ways to travel in the
universe can scientists develop it in
the near future hundred
a century century and a half
to develop other methods okay first of
all it's not almost impossible to travel
faster than the speed of light it is
impossible
to travel at the speed of light or
faster impossible zero chance
that's just what the
laws of physics tell us so it's not
almost impossible it's 100
impossible
of course nowadays there is talk of warp
drive technologies
there are certain solutions of
einstein's field equations that uh
allow you to be to create a bubble of
space time that travels within space
travels
of in some ways faster than the speed of
light that that is still all
hypothetical
we're not still not sure if it is
feasible but even if that happens it's a
couple of centuries in the future at
least a century in the future what we
can do right now is to try is to try and
accelerate
spacecraft to significant percentages of
the speed of light maybe 20 or 30
percent of the speed of light that can
be achieved
in the next decade or so but what kind
of spacecraft small spacecraft so there
is a project called
breakthrough star shot
which proposes
using
radiation pressure
photonic pressure using lasers pulsed
laser array arrays of pulsed lasers
to accelerate small micro spacecraft to
20 or 30 the speed of light and to send
the entire big fleet of a thousand two
thousand spacecraft small ones
to the nearest star proxima centauri
and to send back images and data from
there
so that technology could be achievable
in the next 10 or 20 years
that could happen
from the perspective of physics it's
completely feasible it's completely
possible it's only a question of
developing the technology the lasers
that can do that
and
those spacecraft will have to be tiny
small spacecraft just essentially little
chips
with some optical elements to take uh
images and and some transmitters to send
to send the data back to earth
so that kind of thing could happen in
the next 10 20 years and if we can
accelerate the spacecraft to about 30 of
the speed of light they could reach
proxima centauri in
two three or four decades
and then you would need another four
years for the signals to come back to
earth
so within half a century we could have
the first
close-up images
of
a different star system so that is very
much possible
but
warp technology is still very much
science fiction
that i don't see that happening for the
next century or so
okay beerup says in theoretical physics
will we ever get a final answer every
time there has been some research done
instead of answers
we only come up with more and more
questions
this is a matter of concern but at the
same time it's a perfect example of how
beautiful
our universe and physics is it's endless
so will we ever get a final answer no
i know we won't get a final answer so
right now
excuse me
right now we understand less than five
percent of the universe
more than 95 percent of the universe is
dark we don't know what it is we don't
know what the laws of physics are that
that govern it
there may be new physics there will be
new forces out there
there is something called dark matter
there is something called dark energy
which collectively makes up more than 95
percent of the mass energy composition
of the universe
and we don't know anything about it
so we understand
less than five percent of the universe
and even that understanding is rough and
rudimentary even the standard model is
not perfect
there are there could be
cracks appearing in the standard model
of the physics as well
so uh that's where we are so why do i
say we will never get the final answer
because we are not gods
we have a small
limited intellect there are limits to
human intelligence let's not start
believing we will understand everything
we are just a species of monkey
we are the highest evolved ape on the
planet that's all we are
yesterday we were climbing trees and
eating bananas now we are doing quantum
mechanics
it's just a small step there are lots of
other steps we need to take to to
actually start understanding the
universe properly and maybe
the limitations of our small tiny
intellect
are such that we may never understand
the universe
unless we evolve to something much
higher in a few million years perhaps
so
and yet it is not bad it's not a
question of concern for me
i mean if you get all the fine of all
the final answers then after that what
are we going to do
there will be nothing left to find there
will be nothing left to discover if we
have the final answer
as long as there are things that we have
not discovered there is a mystery
in the universe and what's more
interesting and exciting than mystery
why do we watch movies because there is
a mystery we want to solve
why do we read novels
because there are mysteries in there we
want to
uncover the mystery we want to get the
final answer
it's the journey that's interesting the
final answer is okay the my journey is
over
right so uh
plus of the universe is unknown to us
which i think is
fantastic
it's so exciting there is so much we can
discover so i think it's great and i
don't think we will ever get the final
answer which is fine by me which is fine
alpha beta says like the sun has an
important role in life making planets
and so on what role does a black hole
have in the universe
black holes are a big mystery they have
a very significant role to play
black holes seem to have been the seeds
of the early galaxies every major galaxy
most major most galaxies that we know of
have a supermassive black hole at the
center which keeps which holds the
galaxy together so it is that central
supermassive black hole that
that essentially holds the entire
structure together with its massive
gravity
recently uh the event horizon telescope
was able to take the snapshot of the
supermassive black hole at the center of
our own galaxy
so that happened just this week i think
or last week
so it's the second black hole ever
imaged obviously it's the it's the image
of the
accretion disk around the black hole on
the black hole itself which is dark but
that's how it is so black holes
have one role they hold galaxies
together
and we can feel the the gravitational
effects of the black hole we just don't
realize it
every gravitating
object in the universe exerts a
gravitational force on us we feel the
the effects whether we realize it or not
we feel it
so the supermassive black hole at the
center of our galaxy we can right now i
can right now
experience its its effects but i'm not
quite sure where it's coming from that's
how it is so there is one thing they
hold galaxies together secondly
they may be a significant percentage of
the dark matter of the universe
in the
very early
phase of the universe during the
before inflation and even after
inflation during the reheating epoch it
is believed that because of quantum
fluctuations
enormous quantities of microscopic
black holes
may have been produced
these are called primordial black holes
and if these black holes possibly formed
bound states stable bound states and
survived
then they would possibly form a
significant percentage of the dark
matter
in the universe today that's my theory
it's published
i'm a co-author of that so uh so black
holes could play lots of roles we still
don't know what black holes are really
right many of the objects we
think
are black holes may end up being
something else who knows
so uh
but it's clear that black holes play a
significant role in the universe they
provide the gravitational framework for
the galaxies and they may have a
significant role to play in dark matter
itself we know dark matter exists
everywhere right now in this room where
i'm sitting there is a wind of dark
matter flowing through me
but we don't we don't feel its effects
because it is a purely gravitating
particle or class of particles and it's
very small apparently
so this dark matter going through me
right now through me
through me inside me and i don't feel it
so that also could be in some ways
related to microscopic black holes
perhaps
but it all is still a matter of
just theory we still lack the means to
actually experimentally test all of
these things
so maybe in the future maybe hopefully
in our lifetimes
chi-ching says how not to overthink when
one is not busy or not working
see the mind
is a thinking machine
in in indian
philosophy the mind is considered to be
one of the sense organs
right and the mind it always thinks
whether you are
busy whether you're working whether
you're actually actively studying
something
actively participating in some activity
or whether you're sitting idle the mind
is always at work it's always thinking
and
even when we are sleeping the mind is
thinking and we call it dreams
so we experience dreams most of these
dreams we forget some of them we may
remember
but everybody dreams and that is the
subconscious mind at work we don't quite
know what is the purpose of dreaming i
think the question is different
obviously how not to overthink
so overthinking is just the mind
constantly going in all different
directions all kinds of thoughts coming
to your mind
worries
and random noise in the mind the mind is
full of noise
so
how not to overthink takes practice
and the best way of doing it is through
meditation
and the starting point of meditation is
breath control
controlling your breath
and the easiest way of learning breath
control is by a pranayama
so in pranayama you control your breath
then you focus on your breath and you
control it
in variety in a variety of ways and if
you can learn that then you will be able
to
start meditating effectively even that
takes time
but meditation is all about calming the
mind stealing it quieting it
and when anybody anyone
starts or tries meditating for the first
time it is extremely frustrating because
the mind rebels
against your attempt to calm to calm it
and to quiet it
the more you try the more noisy it gets
and the more rebellious the mind gets
but you have to persevere it takes weeks
months sometimes
but eventually there's a breakthrough
and you can you get and you get better
at that
and over time you get really good at it
and then that's when you're calm and
focused
so it's a process i think this is
something that happens to everybody
everybody's mind is always constantly
jibbering jabbering away it's a noisy
machine
um
so yeah i think the best way is to
is to meditate
and meditate regularly you can start
with 10 minutes a day
and even before you start meditating you
can start with
breath control which is pranayama
so it's something you have to develop
it's it's a skill it's essentially a
skill that you develop over a long
period of time
and if you are a teenager or something
it's great you have plenty of time to do
that so by the time you're 18 or 20 you
will be well versed in that
so don't get frustrated if it doesn't
work at first
persevere
take it one day at a time start with 10
minutes at a time and eventually you
will get good at it and you will be able
to
calm the mind down and that has immense
benefits in all aspects of life
so great question and all the best
okay the next question is by akash and
akash asks this might be too specific
but i am asking anyway
because you have experience in this too
software engineering versus data science
which of these are more impactful and
more in demand
in the modern evolving world that's a
good question so these are two things
two separate things but there is a lot
of overlap also between software
development in data science
so data scientists they essentially what
they do is uh
they research and develop algorithms
machine learning algorithms that's what
data scientists do software engineers
that develop software they focus on the
software development life cycle right
they do things like creating
infrastructure automation testing
maintenance of software designing
software designing software products
apps and all that software pro engineers
focus on programming
object-oriented programming and all that
data science has a focus on statistics
it has a focus on data analytics and
predictive analytics
on data sets you are working with data
sets you're doing data manipulation
you're creating models and things like
that so that is all about data science
both are impactful both are in demand i
think if you if you
look up the
statistics i think data scientists today
earn slightly more
than software engineers
as of today i am i'm talking about u.s
data u.s statistics but
it would apply to other countries as
well i'm sure so i think data scientists
they earn slightly more and data science
is increasingly more in demand because
data is the new oil isn't it
there is so much data being generated
every second today in the world data
metadata all that and that is where the
real sociology comes in because if you
have this entire data set of every
person you can actually crunch through
it
through all using algorithms
and you can actually uncover the entire
psyche of the person the psychology of
the person the the behavioral patterns
thought patterns everything if you have
the right data
and that is extraordinarily powerful
in the hands of the right people or
extremely extraordinarily dangerous as
well
so i think that there's a great future
for for data science and data analytics
it can be really impactful
and it is certainly going to be more and
more in demand in the
modern evolving world software
engineering is also never going to go
out of existence because software
engineering is all about creating
solutions and maintaining solutions and
evolving solutions to various problems
so there is a lot of overlap
where these two fields
merge come together
data scientists would obviously need to
know some programming and all that
software engineers obviously have to
work with data when they're developing
apps or all that so there's a lot of
overlap
so uh you could either go into pure data
science
or you could go into a bit of both but i
think in the long run data science has a
lot of demand and and a lot of scope for
growth and progress
as a career option
okay vikrant says ambassador kaju once
said that pakistan will always be
allowed to stay afloat
irrespective of any crisis economic or
otherwise because no country wants a
nuclear somalia
what are your thoughts
so i am not aware of this quote maybe he
said that
possible
but it's an interesting quote it's an
interesting idea it's an interesting
thought
so
pakistan will always be allowed to stay
afloat
because nobody wants a nuclear
somalia
well
i think this is the perspective of the
west
pakistan is far away from the west
but they don't want a nuclear state
which is a rogue state with no
governance which is essentially what
somalia is
but from the perspective of india
a nuclear pakistan or a nuclear somalia
is the same thing
it is nuclear weapons in the raw in the
hands of the wrong people
so uh from india's perspective i am sure
the us see the real thing is this
the reason why pakistan was created
and the reason why pakistan still exists
it's it has still been allowed but it is
still allowed to exist is to keep on
it's to keep india on the back foot it's
to counter balance india is it's to keep
bleeding india the americans financed
pakistani terrorism in india from the
1980s onwards for the best part of two
two and a half decades
so they used pakistan as a means of of
destabilizing and bleeding india right
that is the real purpose of pakistan
it's not about not wanting a nuclear
somalia
and they the west doesn't want india to
rise beyond a certain point
and india is currently
on a trajectory of rising much higher
than they want in dead rise so pakistan
becomes indispensable in that position
in in that scenario
so they would not want pakistan to
to be destroyed to disintegrate they
would want pakistan to always remain
there
to counter balance india
right so that is the real reason why
pakistan exists and the reason why it
has been allowed to stay afloat not
because they are concerned about a
nuclear somalia and rogue nuclear
weapons they are concerned about india's
rise
that's the real problem
from india's perspective
pakistan is a problem
as long as pakistan exists on the
western border we will always have
problems
and even
if hypothetically some government had
given kashmir away the problem would
have not gone away it's not the problem
the issue is not kashmir
pakistan
seeks india as an existential threat
that's what they claim
but the real thing is that it's a tool
in the hands of the west to key to to
keep on disturbing
destabilizing india
if western interference was not there
tomorrow india could buy out pakistan's
nuclear weapons and buy out the
pakistani generals
they have a price their mercenaries you
give them enough money you meet their
price and they will hand over their
country to you
and they will go and live in the west
that's what they will do
so the real reason why pakistan exists
is that is because
it is a valuable
counterbalance to india in the eyes and
in the hands of the west it's a western
tool and recently it's become a chinese
tool as well and they see it in the same
light
so that is the utility
that pakistan has
for the west and for china and that's
why it has been allowed to keep on
existing
so it is for india to solve the problem
nobody is going to solve india's
problems except india itself
so it is the current leadership and
future leaders who will have to tackle
this problem and to solve the problem
once and for all it can be solved
time will show us
okay let's take a few live chat
questions shall we
let's take a few live live chat
questions
if you all have questions let me know
now let's go
okay
do we have questions do we have
questions
shweta says what is this helium three
found on the moon all about
so helium-3 is an isotope it's it's an
isotope of helium helium is helium-2
the helium atom has
two protons
and two electrons going around that
that's how it is it stays neutral helium
three has two protons in the nucleus and
an extra neutron
so its atomic number is three and that
is helium three it's a heavier isotope
of the element helium and it is found in
abundance
on the moon on in the regolith which is
the lunar soil the topsoil of the moon
because of the constant bombardment of
the solar radiation and cosmic rays
that's what
has created this over this abundance of
helium-3 atoms
on the surface of the moon and helium-3
is believed is
is an excellent
nuclear fuel for next generation fusion
reactors
as of today we have not been able to
uh
to create
controlled fusion
on on on the earth
we have event we have been able to
create fusion reactions which have been
uncontrolled and that's what a
thermonuclear
explosion is it's a fission fusion
reaction
but if you can control fusion then that
will give you an even better source of
energy than a nuclear reactor which is
all about fission the fission reaction
so
so right now there are projects going on
which are which whose aim is to create a
fusion reactor a sustainable controlled
fusion reaction on on earth
which has still not succeeded but maybe
it will happen in the next 10 20 years
so when fusion reactions become fusion
reactors become a reality
that's when helium 3 comes in it's going
to be an excellent fuel for these
reactors
and it is found
in it is very rare on earth
but it's
found in great abundance
in the lunar
soil
so that is what this is all about i
think dr apg abdul kalam had spoken
about this that the the lunar helium-3
is an excellent
is going to be an excellent fuel for
future
fusion reactors so that's what it is all
about
okay
how to understand physics start from the
very basics start from understanding
mathematics
then start with the abcs of physics like
school level
and once you are good with that go to
the higher level higher level higher
level
and in a few years you'll be able to
understand physics well
depending on your progress and your
speed of
and the speed at which you uh
absorb new information and the amount of
hard work that you put in it's a process
okay what's your thoughts on western
channels bashing india
are they doing so because we abstain
they are doing it because they don't
want india to rise and they are uh
they are worried about india's rise
on the global scenario they see the
western channels belong to the western
countries western europe and the us
and this entire
region the so-called western
civilization it's actually the u.s
empire
right and the u.s doesn't want india to
rise beyond a certain certain limit
because then india will become the next
china
if it is allowed to keep on rising
so
that's why they have embarked upon this
entire phase this entire campaign
concerted
protracted campaign of demonizing and
bashing
india and lecturing india and bullying
india and telling india to get in line
so it's all over the western media it's
all over twitter it's all over social
media all these think tanks like rand
corporation and whatever else
and even lots of indian puppets
in the in the indian media
they're all doing the same thing
so it's not about india abstaining it's
about india pursuing an independent
foreign policy
they don't want india to pursue
independent foreign policy they want
india to tow their line and do what they
telling them to do
which essentially makes india an
american vasal state which is not going
to happen
so india is
not towing their line india is pursuing
an independent foreign policy india is
pursuing a strategy of multi-alignment
multilateralism
india wants a multi-polar world as long
as india pursues this foreign policy
a multilateral world is
going to going to be there and they
don't want a multilateral world they
want a bilateral world good and bad they
will say we are good china is bad they
only want two powers
as long as india is independent like
this
there are more than two powers
so that's the whole thing that's the
whole game that has been played and
that's why they are bashing india
and that actually is a great complement
to our foreign policy that they are so
upset about it because we are looking
out for our own
national interest
okay what else do we have
neil says how to read books correctly
how to remember for a long time how to
use in real life
um many people say that they have a
problem they don't remember things that
they read in the books and all so the
thing is very simple if you are if you
don't find it interesting you will not
remember it it's like this go and watch
a movie which is very boring
chances are after a week's time you'll
remember nothing of it
i recently watched this movie
multiverse of madness
last week
i remember next to nothing about it it
was so boring there was no storyline
so if you watch a movie that you find
boring in your opinion then you will
remember nothing
or almost nothing and similarly if you
if you read a book if you force yourself
to read a book that you find boring you
won't remember anything but if you watch
a really exciting interesting movie
after three years you'll remember the
entire storyline similarly if you read a
book that's really interesting you will
remember it for a long time so how to
read books correctly
before you even open a book look at the
title what does that the does the title
say the title gives you a promise
the title tells you that this is what's
inside the book
so before you open the book and start
reading make a list of five questions or
ten questions that you would like to
have the book answer for you
and then look through the book and find
the relevant portion where your question
is answered
so if you have five questions that you
hope the book will answer if it can
answer all five great read the whole
book and you may find it very
interesting
but if you find that the book doesn't
answer the questions that you have or if
it doesn't answer them satisfactorily
then maybe it's not the right book for
you
so it's not about it being a good book
or a bad book
it may not be the right book for you
so the best way to approach reading a
book is to first
have a set of questions
or have a set of topics
about which you want information about
which you seek information and when you
find the information you will not forget
it because you are looking for it
and and that's not the only way to read
a book obviously some books will have
information that you may find
interesting even if you don't if you
even if you have not thought about it
but to start off in your journey of
reading books and retain information
start with this list of questions before
you even open a book
that way you will be able to remember
for a long time if the book can answer
your questions
and how to use it in real life well if
you read a book of philosophy you may
not be able to re use it in real life
if you read a book about tomato
gardening you will not be able to use it
in economics or
so
so if you read a book that has
applications in real life
and if you're able to remember it
you'll be able to use it in real life
that's how it will go sir
okay
the bricks were made by space
enthusiasts who made bricks from mixture
similar to soil on the moon
uh this was kept in mind to make a base
etc all right so great thank you for
letting me know
okay what else what else
can we find new elements in asteroid
mining like vibranium vibranium i think
it's some fictional
element right
so
we cannot find science fiction elements
anywhere in the universe we can only
find the the elements that are in the
periodic table even elements that have
not been discovered yet but the periodic
table can predict elements that will
will be discovered in the future so only
those elements can be found anywhere in
the universe now when it comes to
asteroid mining that's not going to
happen anytime soon
it's not like we have asteroids
everywhere it will take a great amount
of resources to just to reach an
asteroid because the asteroids are
typically in the
region between the orbits of mars and
jupiter
right that's very far away from here so
just to reach an asteroid and that that
entire region of space is mostly and
empty space
the average distance between two any
twice there are just several millions of
kilometers it's almost empty space
so asteroid mining is could be a pipe
dream it could be really prohibitively
expensive but if you can find a big
asteroid and you can actually mine it
you may be able to
find great amounts of metals and useful
things which may kind of crash earth's
economy if you can bring it back to
earth
so
that's
what it is about
okay do we see something else do we have
any other interesting questions
uh let me take one more question before
i am done
okay this is the question i must have
answered 300 times but let's take it
if aryan invasion theory is a myth why
is bharat called aryawath what is the
origin of the word aryan the word arya
is a sanskrit word which means civilized
noble
well-behaved
that's what it means it is not an ethnic
term
it means noble and civilized and
cultured that's what
area means
it is not an ethnic current connotation
the persians
who
left india several thousand years ago
they started using the word arya as an
ethnic term as an ethnic self designator
and that's how it this word came into
eventually made its way to europe and
they started calling the indians and
iranians aryans and then the white
supremacists stole it
and they started using it to denote the
white race
so arya vrat means the land of the
civilized and noble people it means all
of all all indians are arya that's what
it means
so that is the origin of the word arya
let me take one more question
let me take one more question something
interesting
why do we dream
do we dream of dre of immense events
occurring in alternate realities
we don't know why we dream
that's a mystery nobody has been able to
answer neither neurologists or
psychiatrists or psychologists or
anybody
we still don't quite know why we dream
we don't know the mechanism of dreaming
we don't know the mechanism of
consciousness whether it is something
that emerges out of the brain it comes
from somewhere else we don't know we
don't quite know some people would say
that dreams are what you experience
in a parallel universe
there is a multiverse out there and
there is a you in each universe and when
you sleep you connect with the you in
that other universe in one of the other
universes and you experience the reality
they are living that's what some people
say that is science fiction obviously or
fantasy
so that's
where that's all speculation we don't
quite know
why we dream nobody has been able to
solve the mystery of dreaming of
sleeping why do we sleep why do we need
sleep
you keep any animal or human being alive
for a certain period of time of time
they're gonna fall into a coma they may
even die so sleep is
necessary we spent at least a third of
our lives sleeping
and dreaming so what are dreams what is
it is it is it the brain
reconfiguring data and information is it
something else entirely happening
we don't know that is an answer nobody
has so i who am i to answer it i don't
have the answer but it's an interesting
question sometimes the questions are
more interesting than the answers
all right people thank you so much for
another wonderful session wonderful
questions
and let's do it again
soon
maybe not next week next week i'll be
traveling so we may not have a live
stream but after that we will resume
this so thank you so much
and i'll see you soon
thank you take care
bye